Guide to the Newton Theological Institution Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Newton Theological Institution Records
1825-1965
RG 276
Yale University Divinity School Library
46
(53 boxes)
These are the official archives of Newton Theological Institution, a seminary of the Baptist Church, which formally affiliated with Andover Theological Seminary in 1965 to become Andover Newton Theological School.
Newton Theological Institution
Biographical / Historical
In 1825, a group of ministers of the Boston Baptist Association met at First Baptist Church of Boston and decided to found a Baptist seminary in the Boston area. The group raised the funds necessary to purchase and repair the 80-acre Peck estate in Newton, Massachusetts, and Irah Chase was appointed the first professor of biblical theology. Newton Theological Institution was incorporated by the Legislature on February 21, 1826, and the first classes were held November 28, 1826. The graduate seminary was formally affiliated with the group now known as American Baptist Churches USA, which is the oldest Baptist denomination in America. In 1931 Andover Theological Seminary moved to Newton Theological Institution's Newton Centre campus, and the two schools became affiliated, forming Andover Newton Theological School. In 1965, the two Schools formally merged. (Sources: Today's Ministry Commemorative Bicentennial Issue 1807-2007; Wikipedia: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newton_Theological_Institution accessed 8 June 2007)
Chronology
1825 Newton Theological Institution founded in Newton Centre, Massachusetts
1826 Newton Theological Institution incorporated by the Massachusetts Legislature
1931 At invitation of Newton Theological Institution, Andover Theological Seminary relocates to Newton Center, Massachusetts
1965 Newton Theological Institution and Andover Theological Seminary formally merge to form Andover Newton Theological School
Scope and Contents
The records have been maintained in the order in which they were received from Andover Newton Theological School. The archives of Newton Theological Institution have been organized into 10 series.
Arrangement
Organized into ten series: I. Trustees, II. Early Records, III. Faculty, IV. Students, V. Alumnae/i, VI. Publications, VII. Events, VIII. Library, IX. Audiovisual, X. Realia.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Andover Newton Theological School, 2017.
Newton Theological Institution; Andover Newton Theological School
- Trustees, Series I
  - President
    - Correspondence, 1886, 1894, 1908-1957, no date (Box 1, Folder 1-9)
    - Herrick correspondence, 1926-1937, no date (Box 53, Folder 1-6)
    - Horr correspondence, 1916–1919 (Box 53, Folder 7)
    - Lutherans and Southern Baptists: conferences, 1910–1912 (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
    - Lutherans and Southern Baptists: conferences, 1910–1912 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Reports, 1902–1960 (Box 1, Folder 13-24)
  - Secretary
    - Minutes, 1826–1946 (Box 2, Folder 2-7)
    - Minutes, 1936–1965 (Box 3, Folder 1-18)
    - Correspondence, 1828–1957 (Box 3, Folder 19-32)
    - Resolutions and ad hoc committee reports, 1829–1912 (Box 3, Folder 33-38)
    - Resolutions and ad hoc committee reports, 1913–1957 (Box 4, Folder 1-6)
  - Secretary of the Seminary
    - Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 7-51)
  - Treasurer
    - Correspondence: incoming, 1826–1885 (Box 5, Folder 1-19)
    - Correspondence: incoming, 1886–1942 (Box 6, Folder 1-13)
    - Correspondence: outgoing, 1873–1888 (Box 6, Folder 14-15)
    - Correspondence: outgoing, 1888–1889 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Account books, 1855–1938 (Box 11, Folder 1-5)
    - Accounts, 1880 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Annual reports, 1825–1912 (Box 7, Folder 2-16)
    - Annual reports, 1913–1940 (Box 8, Folder 1-6)
    - Annual reports, 1941–1954 (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
    - Annual statement, 1869–1980 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Annuity matters, 1929–1953 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Audit reports, 1920–1953 (Box 46, Folder 1-20)
    - Cash book, 1885–1896 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Trial balance, 1907–1932 (Box 24)
  - Financial Secretary
    - Subject files: A-F, circa 1853-1957 (Box 8, Folder 7-34)
    - Subject files: F-S (Box 10, Folder 1-56)
    - Subject files: subscriptions and pledges, 1906–1918 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Contracts, deeds, mortgages, trusts, 1868–1956 (Box 12, Folder 1-19)
    - Taxes, correspondence, Veterans Bureau, 1919–1963 (Box 13, Folder 1-5)
    - Vouchers, circa 1825-1886 (Box 12, Folder 20-22)
    - Vouchers, 1831–1889 (Box 13, Folder 6-23)
    - Vouchers, 1890–1932 (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
    - Wills, Various (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Committees
    - Collected committee reports, 1891–1907 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Buildings and Grounds Committee, 1894-1952, no date
    - Buildings and Grounds Committee, 1893-1940, no date (Box 17, Folder 1-15)
    - Committee for Providing Instruction in Prof. Anderson's Dept., 1868–1869 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Committee of Distribution, 1884–1894 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Committee of Nine, 1907 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Committee on Changes, 1845 (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Committee on Nominations, 1895 (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Committee on Scholarships, 1896 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Examining Committee, 1834–1946 (Box 14, Folder 23-29)
    - Executive Committee: minutes, 1854–1946 (Box 14, Folder 30-34)
    - Executive Committee: reports and correspondence, 1854–1913 (Box 14, Folder 35-39)
    - Executive Committee: reports and correspondence, 1913–1927 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Executive Committee: correspondence, 1915–1947 (Box 15, Folder 2-8a)
    - Executive Committee: obituaries, 1899–1912 (Box 15, Folder 8b)
    - Executive Committee: votes, 1860–1901 (Box 15, Folder 8c)
    - Faculty Committee: degree granting suggestions, no date (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Faculty Committee: reports, 1836-1949, no date (Box 15, Folder 10-20)
    - Finance Committee, 1849-1941, no date (Box 15, Folder 21-29)
    - Gordon School Committee, 1897–1915 (Box 15, Folder 36-38)
    - Library Committee: correspondence, minutes, and reports, 1848-1947, no date (Box 15, Folder 30-35)
- Early Records, Series II
  - General topics, including Backus Historical Society, correspondence, histories, Newton Cemetery Corporation, and scrapbook of publications and correspondence, 1827-1933, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 1-30)
  - Bequests, 1800s (Box 53, Folder 7-18)
  - Lawsuit: NTI vs. Lucius L. Clarke, 1877–1878 (Box 53, Folder 19)
  - Scholarships, 1800s (Box 53, Folder 20-31)
- Faculty, Series III
  - Faculty meeting minutes (5 vols.), 1825–1932 (Box 16, Folder 31-35)
  - General: includes correspondence, reports, and circulars, 1830-1921, no date (Box 18, Folder 1-7)
  - Course documentation: lectures, course outlines, and syllabi, no date (Box 18, Folder 8-26)
  - Course documentation of professors Anderson, Donovan, Horr, Nordell, and Vaughn, 1937-1938, no date (Box 19–23)
- Students, Series IV
  - General
    - General, 1837-1934, no date (Box 25, Folder 1-3)
    - Addresses, 1892–1923 (Box 25, Folder 4-92)
    - Applications, circa 1897-1911 (Box 25, Folder 92-94)
    - Applications, 1911–1944 (Box 26, Folder 1-12)
    - Autographs of NTI Men, 1839–1886 (Box 27)
    - Lecture notes and recitations (by professor), 1894-1899, 1929 (Box 26, Folder 13-14)
    - Lecture notes and recitations (by professor), 1862-1894, no date (Box 28, Folder 1-15)
    - Lecture notes and recitations (by professor), 1825-1874, no date (Box 29, Folder 1-11)
  - Student organizations
    - Boarding Club, 1865–1885 (Box 30, Folder 1-4)
    - Boarding Club, 1945–1947 (Box 30, Folder 1-4)
    - Boarding Club, 1924–1931 (Box 31, Folder 10-11)
    - Evangelistic Band, circa 1928 (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Knowles Rhetorical Society, 1832–1900 (Box 29, Folder 13-16)
    - Knowles Rhetorical Society, 1852–1876 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Messianic Prophecy, 1915 (Box 29, Folder 17)
    - Missionary Society, 1835-1860, 1903 (Box 29, Folder 18-19)
    - Society of Inquiry (includes photograph album), 1827–1871 (Box 29, Folder 20-27)
    - Society of Inquiry, 1838-1863, 1909 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Society of Inquiry: constitution and minutes, 1827–1911 (Box 32, Folder 1-2)
    - Student Association, 1926 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Student Volunteer Band, 1898–1924 (Box 31, Folder 4-9)
    - The Ten: record book, 1893–1894 (Box 12)
  - Student Papers
    - Student Papers, 1897–1939 (Box 2, Folder 13-20)
- Alumnae/i, Series V
  - Autographs, no date (Box 31, Folder 22)
  - Activities, circa 1898-1955 (Box 31, Folder 23-29)
  - Annual meeting minutes, 1834–1844 (Box 31, Folder 30-31)
  - Annual meeting minutes, 1845–1950 (Box 33, Folder 1-3)
  - Bylaws and incorporation, 1900 (Box 33, Folder 4a)
  - Church Cooperation Committee, 1927 (Box 33, Folder 4b)
  - Class correspondence (by class), 1862–1949 (Box 33, Folder 5-28)
  - Clerk's Records, 1950–1962 (Box 33, Folder 29a-b)
  - Correspondence: general, 1898, 1926-1928 (Box 33, Folder 29c-36)
  - Correspondence: national conference, 1927 (Box 33, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence: Everett C. Herrick, 1926–1928 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee: correspondence and minutes, 1899-1950, no date (Box 34, Folder 2-3)
  - Fundraising (Second Century Fund, Special Gifts Committee, List Committee), 1919–1928 (Box 34, Folder 4-24)
  - Leaflets, 1879, 1898, 1901, 1920, 1923 (Box 34, Folder 25)
  - Membership, 1928-1929, n.d. (Box 34, Folder 26)
  - Missionaries List, 1830–1922 (Box 34, Folder 27)
  - Necrology report, 1856–1866 (Box 35, Folder 1-60, 66)
  - Organization (Box 35, Folder 61)
  - Progress report luncheons (Box 35, Folder 62)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1891–1925, 1952-1954 (Box 33, Folder 63-65)
- Publications, Series VI
  - General: Regular Calendar of Business, 1889 (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - General: School hymns, 1893 (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - Addresses and other writings: Everett Carleton Herrick, circa 1926 (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Addresses and other writings: George Edwin Horr, 1919, no date (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Addresses and other writings: Alvah Hovey, 1854 (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - Addresses and other writings: James D. Knowles, 1839 (Box 36, Folder 6a)
  - Addresses and other writings: The Newton Theological Institution: Equipment for Service, 1924 (Box 36, Folder 6b)
  - Brochures, 1897-1944, no date (Box 36, Folder 7-11)
  - Bulletin: Newton Theological Institution, 1906–1939 (Box 38, Folder 1-9)
  - Bulletin: The Newton Missionary Bulletin, 1904 (Box 38, Folder 16)
  - Catalogs: annual, triennial, and general, 1835–1908 (Box 36, Folder 12-27)
  - Catalogs: annual, 1908–1931 (Box 37, Folder 1-15)
  - Catalogs: general (address book), 1826–1943 (Box 38, Folder 10-11)
  - Charter, By-Laws, and Rules and Regulations, 1849–1957 (Box 38, Folder 12-14)
  - Circulars, 1898-1901, no date (Box 38, Folder 15)
  - Newsletter: The Newtonian, 1903–1904 (Box 38, Folder 17-18)
  - Programme of Public Exercises, 1900–1931 (Box 39, Folder 1-29)
- Events, Series VII
  - Events by date, 1828-1935, no date (Box 39, Folder 31-57)
  - 400th Anniversary of Lutheran Reformation, 1917 (Box 39, Folder 58)
  - Anniversary: 100th, 1925 (Box 39, Folder 59-72)
  - Anniversary: 150th, 1975 (Box 39, Folder 73)
  - Anniversary essays, 1828–1859 (Box 39, Folder 74-76)
  - Anniversary programs, 1828–1851 (Box 40, Folder 1-2)
  - Annual banquet, 1922 (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - Annual meeting of the theological seminaries, 1876, 1898 (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Baccalaureate service, 1896, 1931-1954 (Box 40, Folder 5-6)
  - Chapel dedication, 1897 (Box 40, Folder 7)
  - Commencement, 1893-1931, no date (Box 40, Folder 8-11)
  - Conference of Baptist Seminaries, 1919 (Box 40, Folder 12)
  - Conference of Theological Schools, 1918 (Box 40, Folder 13)
  - Conference: The Newton Conference, 1921, 1924 (Box 40, Folder 14)
  - Convocation: leadership convocation, no date (Box 40, Folder 15)
  - Dedications and reopenings, 1866–1931 (Box 40, Folder 16-22)
  - Dinners, 1897-1898, 1947-1954, no date (Box 40, Folder 23-24)
  - Inauguration: Horr, 1909 (Box 40, Folder 25)
  - Lectures, 1908 (Box 40, Folder 26)
  - Lectureship: Green, 1922 (Box 40, Folder 27)
  - Recital, 1923 (Box 40, Folder 28)
  - Thanksgiving, 1898-1915, no date (Box 40, Folder 29)
  - Tree planting ceremony (Helen Barrett Montgomery), 1945 (Box 40, Folder 30)
  - Unveilings, 1903–1916 (Box 40, Folder 31-33)
- Library, Series VIII
  - Accessions, 1889–1908 (Box 40, Folder 1-3)
  - Accessions, 1948–1955 (Box 40, Folder 34)
  - Account books, 1886–1911 (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - Account books, 1908–1917 (Box 41, Folder 1-2)
  - Accounts, 1866–1948 (Box 40, Folder 35-40)
  - Acquisition notes, circa 1857 (Box 40, Folder 41)
  - Alphabetical catalog, 1867-1889, no date (Box 42, Folder 37-7)
  - Annual reports, 1863–1945 (Box 40, Folder 42-42)
  - Bibliographies, no date (Box 40, Folder 44)
  - Bills, 1856 (Box 40, Folder 45)
  - Biography and sermons list, 1836–1928 (Box 40, Folder 46)
  - Blueprint, no date (Box 40, Folder 47)
  - Bookplates, no date (Box 40, Folder 48)
  - Books circulated, 1881–1887 (Box 42, Folder 8)
  - Books donated by E. L. Magoon, no date (Box 40, Folder 49)
  - Books drawn from library, 1854-1857, n.d. (Box 40, Folder 50-53)
  - Books in course of publication and series of books, 1889–1907 (Box 40, Folder 54)
  - Books ordered by faculty, 1876 (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Catalog, 1833 (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Catalog, chronological, 1862–1872 (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - Catalog, chronological, 1887-1889, no date (Box 42, Folder 10-11)
  - Charge book, 1868–1889 (Box 43, Folder 4-5)
  - Charge book, 1876–1881 (Box 42, Folder 9)
  - Charge book, 1884–1890 (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1889–1924 (Box 43, Folder 7-22)
  - Correspondence, 1925–1934 (Box 44, Folder 1-10)
  - Correspondence and record of books returned, sold, mission, 1889-? (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - Donation form, 1880s (Box 44, Folder 11)
  - Expenses, 1894–1907 (Box 44, Folder 12)
  - Hartshorn (J.C.) list of collections of synagogue materials donated, no date (Box 44, Folder 13)
  - Library Committee, 1855–1894 (Box 44, Folder 14-16)
  - Lists, 1927, no date (Box 44, Folder 17)
  - Memoranda, no date (Box 44, Folder 18)
  - Missing books and books disposed of, 1862–1872 (Box 44, Folder 19)
  - Pamphlets, 1866–1890 (Box 44, Folder 20)
  - Periodicals, 1862–1937 (Box 44, Folder 21-24)
  - Portraits in library and chapel, no date (Box 44, Folder 25)
  - Reminiscences, 1919 (Box 44, Folder 26)
  - Shell inventory, no date (Box 44, Folder 27)
  - Stearns book fund, 1900–1903 (Box 44, Folder 28)
- Audiovisual, Series IX
  - Lantern slides of travels taken by an unidentified person; topics include: Middle East, Venice, Greece, circa 1908-1912 (Box 47–48)
  - Photographs and drawings, Topics include: campus scenes, faculty, students, and events, circa 1848-1975 (Box 49–51)
  - Engraving of campus and plans, 1851, 1930 (Box 52)
- Realia, Series X
  - Embosser, no date (Box 53)